<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://mishrakishan.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://mishrakishan.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-01-25T22:49:55+00:00</updated><id>https://mishrakishan.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Darwin Day</title><link href="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/distill/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Darwin Day"/><published>2025-01-10T02:29:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-10T02:29:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/distill</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/distill/"><![CDATA[<blockquote> <p>Sexual Selection ensures that dudes get fancy dresses.</p> </blockquote> <p><img src="https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:720/format:webp/1*odFY9m9MBawrlUePhayATg.png" alt=""/></p> <p>(In Fig: Male Grandalas are blue and Females are the brown or grey ones.)</p> <p>Darwin, in a letter, wrote to Asa Gray, “The sight of a feather in a peacock’s tail, whenever I gaze on it, makes me sick!” The seeming impossibility of explaining the gorgeous but impractical long tail of peacock had been bothering him for some time. He was so curious to know what causes the sexual differences which require some degree of self-consciousness in the males, as weapons by which they fight for the female, or ornaments that attract the opposite sex.</p> <p>His previous theory of ‘Natural Selection’ could only operate to spread a particular feature through a population, no matter how advantageous it might be if the individuals who possessed it, managed to breed and pass it on. Sexual differences between male and female of the same species had bothered him for a long time.</p> <p>But what are the apparent differences between the sexes? As it’s been observed, exotic colour in insects and birds, ornaments like ruffs and crests, the longer manes in male humans, Antlers or horns being so much smaller, or completely absent in some female deer or cattle, the contrasting bright and drab plumage of so many male and female birds and butterflies.</p> <p>After a long period of observation, he came with the idea of Sexual Selection. It’s a mechanism operating alongside natural selection which determines the sexual difference between male and female of the same species. It is a mechanism of two parts — involving physical adaptation in males, but also the aesthetic sense in females, which in many cases played a crucial role in selecting males.</p> <p>“The essence of Darwin’s disruptive genius was his ability to think about nature not as facts— but as a process, as progression, as history,” Mukherjee writes. Darwin’s genius was the awe-inspiring idea of Natural Selection. On December 27, 1831, he circumnavigated from Plymouth, England on HMS Beagle and headed towards Cape Verde to reach the shore of his intimate inquisitiveness surveying expedition of the southern Atlantic and Pacific oceans. As a scientist-in-training his never-ending thoughts of collecting, observing and noticing anything worthy to be noted made him sail the boat for five long years across many islands. During his journey as he writes in his book The Origin of Species, that he strongly felt lonely, nauseated, and dehydrated at times while surviving on a diet of dry raisins and bread. He kept believing in and reminding himself to stay calm and mentally healthy to avoid any propensity for impatience, inaccuracy and misery. As the journey went on, the expected evolutionary biological traits perplexed and thrilled him with joy and confidence, that he began writing and scribbling in his notes and journals. He observed and drew finches, penguins, birds, animals encountered throughout his journey. After five years when he returned to England, his drawings were the evidence of his proposed groundbreaking scientific work and the profound idea of natural selection that he almost had formulated and thoerised. But he was wary to reveal his collection and theories as they were completely contradicting the existed biblical narratives on the origin of species. He writes, “In natural selection, organisms with genetic variations that suit their environment tend to propagate more descendants than organisms of the same species that lack the variation, thus influencing the overall genetic makeup of the species”. Later on, this idea solved many underlying and lurking religious orthodox, biblical stories, biological mysteries and puzzles.</p> <p><img src="https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:720/format:webp/1*rtIJQkPfa1neEWflYvD2tw.jpeg" alt=""/></p> <blockquote> <p><em>The gene — An intimate History’ by Siddharth Mukherjee</em> In his drawing, there was no centre (as in Christianity, God firmly is placed at epicentre: all animals, created by him sprayed outward from the moment of creation). The thirteen types of finches he drew were not created by some divine whim, but by “natural descent” — cascading downward and upward from an original ancestral finch, he asserted.</p> </blockquote> <p><img src="https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:720/format:webp/0*PjEmLTdraH14lLT5.jpg" alt=""/></p> <blockquote> <p><em>A portrait of Charles Darwin and Title Page of ‘The Origin Of Species</em></p> </blockquote> <p>Later, on November 24, 1859, his first book “The Origin of Species” endorsing the theory of Natural Selection and the fundamentals of biological evolution was published. His theory that time was not formally accepted as it was very challenging to the previously acquired wisdom of humankind. It took a while for our society to accept the scientific challenges Darwin made based on the shreds of evidence he collected, a life span he spent and devoted to observations, understandings and pursuit of science. His theory received a general acceptance around 1882, after 52 years of social struggle, almost when Darwin had the last moments of his gratifying endeavour and the invaluable contribution he made to the scientific societies.</p> <p>After he received a good amount of acceptance (validation) to his theory, postcolonial societies led by industrial revolutions extracted a set of ideologies as ‘Social Darwinism’ to define social, political and economic views when imperialism, racism and inequalities were breeding at an immense rate in the society. Darwins’ theory of evolution and Social Darwinism are two different theories where the former is a biological evolution that progresses by sharing biological traits genetically and the later is a societal change that shares morality, intelligence, strength, frugality and many more. Darwin completely despised the transferring-evolution of social values developed by humankind through generations.</p> <p><img src="https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:640/format:webp/0*JcuJI7j-Ob8skckf.jpg" alt=""/></p> <blockquote> <p><em>Photo: Westminster Abbey Library</em> As an afterthought, he added “I think” above the page, as if to signal is the last point of departure from the mainland of biological and theological thoughts. His proposition “I think” above societal incongruity that all species have descended from a common ancestor is now a fundamental concept in science and the idea of survival “Natural Selection: endless forms and most beautiful and most wonderful have been, are being, evolved” is the grassroots of evolutionary biology.</p> </blockquote> <p>==Sometimes we need to really challenge our collective accepted wisdom in order to move forward. Because as long and as much time any theory or wisdom takes to transcend the physical time and persists in society, it gets harder and harder to challenge them and invalidate its gravity.==</p> <p><strong>Science and Technology continuously have been advancing with the progressiveness of society and research but in molecular and evolutionary biology Darwin’s genius and ideas have always remained central to the field.</strong></p> <p>Note: The following (<em>“A beautiful flock of grandalas!”</em>) contrasting colours and subtle differences were also studied by the Handicap Principle supported by many Evolutionary biologists, and is why peacocks have such long tails, even though they are a burden for flight and evading predators.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="writing"/><category term="darwin"/><category term="sexualselection"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Sexual Selection]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Still Vulnerable at 25</title><link href="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/twitter/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Still Vulnerable at 25"/><published>2025-01-10T02:29:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-10T02:29:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/twitter</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/twitter/"><![CDATA[<p>The chair of solitude is so comforting until it’s an unexplainable, suffocating silence that rebels against the pursuit of “living a life in love’, recognition, pity, validation or attention other than any honest attempt to communicate an understanding.” If building castles in the air would be one thing, building haunted devil mansions would be another. And realisation hits hard, and you fall down into an inward spiral in the depths of nowhere.</p> <p>The hot coffee would steam on a bright sunny day as you sit bored on your couch. Unwilling to move muscles, you would remain there, staring into the void while your brain would start to do “the talking”. The talks, most of, if not all the time, would be dark. Scared, you start craving activity. Yet, you wouldn’t want to cut ties with lethargy without a proper closure. So, you would start with a gentle peek out of the window. Muscle movement achieved! Like a yorker right into the black hole, the sun would slap your face tight. “The window was there for a reason!”, your brain wouldn’t seem to give up. You would stare at the world outside. You would wonder at a white feather being kissed by the winds, shining as its manoeuver past you! You would start falling in love with almost everything that you see through the window. “I see. Now what about this?”, our brain cuts in. Then, you would table-fan your head slightly to the sides to find gigantic wings on either side of your shoulders. “Hehe!”, the asshole of a brain would give you a manipulative laugh. It would make you want to use the wings because flying high would give you a different form of high. Adding fuel to the fire, the typical midsummer breeze outside the window would stage a ballet in your face. ” This gets interesting”, your brain grabs a popcorn while you stay there like a total jackass gridlocked by the two differently haunting weapons of choice. The window would almost slap harder as the breeze starts gusting, if not for the latch. It doesn’t stop there. The rooftop that’d been watching everything just above you blows out open and you see light entering and skies smiling at you.</p> <p>One of the quotes by Camus hits right in my face of vulnerability every time I get stuck in a situation like this,</p> <p><em>Sad to still feel so vulnerable. In 25 years I’ll be 57. 25 years then to create a body of work and to find what I’m looking for. After that, old age and death. I know what is most important for me. And I still find a way to give in to little temptations, wasting time of frivolous conversations or fruitless idling about. I’ve mastered two or three things in myself. But how far I am from the kind of superiority that I so badly need.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="writing"/><category term="solitude"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The chair of solitude is so comforting until it’s an unexplainable, suffocating silence that rebels against the pursuit of “living a life in love’, recognition, pity, validation or attention other than any honest attempt to communicate an understanding.” If building castles in the air would be one thing, building haunted devil mansions would be another. And realisation hits hard, and you fall down into an inward spiral in the depths of nowhere.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Love is a funny thing.</title><link href="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/disqus-comments/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Love is a funny thing."/><published>2025-01-07T03:44:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-07T03:44:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/disqus-comments</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/disqus-comments/"><![CDATA[<p>Love is a funny thing. You expect it to be easy. You expect it to be a world of roses and laughs and perfect moments that you find only in movies. You expect your partner to always say the right thing and always know exactly how you feel, or exactly how to react to it. You expect them to calm you down when you’re yelling or to chase you when you run away. You expect so much that you feel entirely, and utterly defeated when something doesn’t exactly match up with all your plans. But that’s the thing, love isn’t a plan. Love is a feeling. It’s that feeling you get when you know you are going to see that person. You are always counting down the minutes, the hours, the days or even months until you will see them again because you love that feeling you have when you are with them.</p> <p>Love is a feeling of perfect happiness. Being in their arms means that everything will be okay and even if it’s really not going to be, you’ll get a feeling that they’ll do whatever they can to make it be, or just to try to make you feel better. It’s that feeling that you are loved for who you are and you love them for who they are. It’s about how they are the first ones you want to talk to when anything is good or bad and how you are always learning something new no matter how long you’ve been together. It’s about changing and being a new person, not necessarily changing your ways or who you are, but wanting to be different and a better person simply cause that person is in your life and you want to be everything to them.</p> <p>Love doesn’t have a certain beginning and it certainly has no end or visible finish line to those deeply in it. Love happens, and it is so incredibly messy. You don’t just automatically love someone. you have to slowly learn to trust; Trust that they don’t cheat on you, trust that they don’t lie to you, trust that they truly admire you, trust that they will always be there for you, trust that they can go to a party and not get high or drunk, trust that you don’t have to worry about them breaking up with you the second you wake up, trust that they will stick up for you trust that you don’t have to worry about them breaking up with you the second you wake up, trust that they will stick up for you, trust that they will never fall in love with another, trust that they won’t just get sick of you, and trust that they want you, like you want them. You want to be with them more to the point where you’re jealous of anyone who tries to be with that person. Then it gets you mad but you get past it, you can’t be jealous anymore. You can’t because you have this undying confidence that this person will never leave you, they will never betray you, and that they would never pick someone else over you, that you’re irreplaceable. That’s when the confidence hits you, that you really do love each other and it’s unbreakable.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="writing"/><category term="love"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Love is a funny thing. You expect it to be easy. You expect it to be a world of roses and laughs and perfect moments that you find only in movies. You expect your partner to always say the right thing and always know exactly how you feel, or exactly how to react to it. You expect them to calm you down when you’re yelling or to chase you when you run away. You expect so much that you feel entirely, and utterly defeated when something doesn’t exactly match up with all your plans. But that’s the thing, love isn’t a plan. Love is a feeling. It’s that feeling you get when you know you are going to see that person. You are always counting down the minutes, the hours, the days or even months until you will see them again because you love that feeling you have when you are with them.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Human cycle of civilization and destruction</title><link href="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/math/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Human cycle of civilization and destruction"/><published>2025-01-02T14:47:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-02T14:47:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/math</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/math/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>“Smooth and smiling faces everywhere, but ruin in their eyes.”</strong> — Jean-Paul Sartre</p> <p>Mohammed Anis, a white-haired man, sitting on a bed amid the rubble, a litter of debris and smokes inside his home that used to be a splendid city apartment, now has been blasted into ruins, rubbish and dust with deep gouges in white walls as his hometown Aleppo was besieged with bombs, mortar fire, and starvation in the aftermath of six-year-long Syrian civil war. White wicker furniture, he used to sit and listen music, has been splintered and scorched.</p> <p>Assad regime has obliterated so much of the city, his great collection of Vintage Cars that even included a replica of Adolf Hitler’s Mercedes, and him. He has his tobacco, music, and samovar. In between the bombs, those are comforts, he found. You see, there are some things that bombs and fighting just can’t kill.</p> <p>As the Photographer reports: “How can you live here,” He asked him. “It’s my home,” Anis answered simply. Like many of Aleppo’s residents, he sleeps in debris. When he saw an old crank-up gramophone at the edge of the bed, perhaps the only thing around him that still works, had survived. Mohammed Anis told him, “I will play it for you… But first, I have to light my pipe. Because I never listen to music without it.” “Anis puffed on his pipe. He seemed to be somewhere else as well. He seemed to forget that we were there. He looked out the window and he had a look on his face of a person watching a beautiful sunset. He sat there, puffing on his broken pipe and staring out the window which has been shattered; and gauzy white curtains, which flap-like wounded white birds, as the music floated over the ruins of his house and the city outside. After six years of war, the Syrians want life. They just want to let the music play.”</p> <p>He put a record on the turntable, and presses the needle down. The man holds his pipe in contemplation and listens to the music in his ruins and the human cycle of civilisation and destruction.</p> <p><em>Source: Correspondent AFP</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="writing"/><category term="philosophy"/><category term="satire"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“Smooth and smiling faces everywhere, but ruin in their eyes.” — Jean-Paul Sartre]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Multilayer DW &amp;amp; Skyrmion-based Spintronic LIF Neuron Model &amp;amp; Devices for Neuromorphic Computing – Kudos: Growing the influence of research</title><link href="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2024/multilayer-dw-skyrmion-based-spintronic-lif-neuron-model-devices-for-neuromorphic-computing-kudos-growing-the-influence-of-research/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Multilayer DW &amp;amp; Skyrmion-based Spintronic LIF Neuron Model &amp;amp; Devices for Neuromorphic Computing – Kudos: Growing the influence of research"/><published>2024-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-12T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2024/multilayer-dw--skyrmion-based-spintronic-lif-neuron-model--devices-for-neuromorphic-computing--kudos-growing-the-influence-of-research</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2024/multilayer-dw-skyrmion-based-spintronic-lif-neuron-model-devices-for-neuromorphic-computing-kudos-growing-the-influence-of-research/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Neuromorphic computing, inspired by the structure and function of the human brain, offers groundbreaking potential for energy-efficient and adaptive computing systems. Unlike traditional computing models, neuromorphic systems operate through spiking neural networks (SNNs), which mimic the dynamic and parallel processing capabilities of biological neurons. These systems excel in real-time data processing, scalability, and robustness, making them ideal candidates for a wide range of applications including perception, image classification, pattern recognition, and machine learning. Traditional implementations of SNNs often rely on CMOS-based hardware, such as IBM's TrueNorth and Intel's Loihi chips, to simulate neural dynamics. However, these devices face significant limitations in terms of energy consumption, scalability, and speed. This study proposes spintronic based neuromorphic devices using domain walls and skyrmions in multilayer ferromagnetic structures to emulate leaky integrate-and-fire neurons. By combining spin–orbit torque, demagnetization energy modulation, and micromagnetic simulations, these devices achieve efficient spike latency, integration density and robust LIF behavior. Integrated into spiking neural networks, they achieve high-density computing, 98% accuracy on MNIST, and 95% on FMNIST, paving the way for scalable, energy-efficient neuromorphic hardware.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Journey uphill</title><link href="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2024/code/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Journey uphill"/><published>2024-12-09T02:09:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-09T02:09:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2024/code</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2024/code/"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:720/format:webp/0*WaiADQdep0uKneTU.jpeg" alt=""/></p> <p>Rafiki is one of my favourite characters from Disney’s ‘The Lion King’. I realised when Simba was sad from the tragic loss of his father and was abandoned by his friends for being purposeless and nihilistic in life. To escape this perpetual feeling, Simba flees away from his Kingdom, Pride Land. At an odd moment, he meets Rafiki, the advisor of his kingdom. Rafiki, as an old wise man, speaks to the inner self of Simba when he needed someone the most to find his lost identity and meaning of his life. He helps Simba rediscover himself when all he was lost, hurt, weak and drowned in the memories of his father and shouldering the guilt of his father’s death. Simba follows Rafiki to find the answers to lessen the burden he was carrying. After a long chase near a pond, a pebble grabs his attention where he sees him reflected as a strong and mighty king, not the immature and adult child he was. As a light sparks in the sky, Simba recalls his father and begs for help from him. The Spark reminds him of his father, and he follows the light-tail until it disappears.</p> <p><img src="https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:624/format:webp/0*F4SwISXfPwTs16k6.jpg" alt=""/></p> <p>Simba sits down sadly again, but Rafiki hits him with his stick — an overhead swing to show how other things (as his stick) can hurt if you are drowned in memories, regrets, and the past. Rafiki reminds him that if he can’t let go of his past, he slowly will degrade and lose his very present that has a promising future. He encourages him to accept his past voluntarily and easily, reminding him that, “An invented past can be useful; yes, It cracks and crumbles under the pressures of life like clay in a season of drought, but it will always bolster you up to make the right choices and save you from drowning in the hardest time when you need yourself the most.” Then, he cracks jokes, tells riddles and solves puzzles to encourage Simba to remember his forthcoming responsibilities for his kingdom and for his father’s sacrifice.</p> <p>Rafiki tells Simba that, in the course of being, we rise and fall and cry and smile, and it is inevitable. But we can transcend through the hurdles and challenges on our path and drive the journey to becoming who we aspire to be. We do mistakes, terrible mistakes. We rant and curse ourselves as we grow mature and realise by digging deeper into ourselves. Realising all of this could be painful for a moment. Well, It must be, Rafiki says, “but you either run away from it so you don’t get hurt or learn from it.” What has been done can not be reversed, but what remains to be done can be done with a better you. After all, anything that happens is not always a positive experience. However, if you frame it right, then almost all the experiences do shape you constructively. I believe that if you correctly articulate your thoughts, have good coping skills, resilience, and believe that you are truly in control of your actions, you can learn something from just about any struggle.</p> <p>Simba begins to feel better after carefully listening to Rafiki’s wise words, so the next time Rafiki illustrates his point, he again swings his stick at Simba. But Simba ducks, demonstrating that he has learned from his pain and past and won’t get hurt again, even though this time it was not overhead, but the hardest, a full cross-body swing. But he saves himself from getting hurt by learning from his experience and loss.</p> <p>We all need Rafiki (who knows the way) to guide us through difficult times in life, particularly when we’re growing up and are highly potent and capable of slaying the dragon. We are dynamite in our 20s. We have to conquer the shadow and fear of the unknown and open up the world of endless possibilities. It’s a continuous cycle of becoming and losing, and it’s never too late to stick to your journey and push the wheels along. Above all, we have to let go of things that hinder our mental peace to move forward forthrightly.</p> <p>After all, we all aspire to be like the stars but to do so, we have to be courageous enough to face the darkness and to keep moving to journey uphill, rather than in the fleeting sense of happiness awaiting the next peak.</p> <p>Also can be read at <a href="https://mishrakishan.medium.com/journey-uphill-5ffe75580945">Medium</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="writing"/><category term="TheLionKing"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Rafiki from The Lion King]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Blog | Imagine Sisyphus Happy ☕</title><link href="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2024/blog-imagine-sisyphus-happy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Blog | Imagine Sisyphus Happy ☕"/><published>2024-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-05-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2024/blog--imagine-sisyphus-happy-</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2024/blog-imagine-sisyphus-happy/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[jack of all trades, master of one.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Journey Uphill</title><link href="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2021/journey-uphill/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Journey Uphill"/><published>2021-04-07T17:53:17+00:00</published><updated>2021-04-07T17:53:17+00:00</updated><id>https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2021/journey-uphill</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2021/journey-uphill/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">‘Darwin’ Day</title><link href="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2021/darwin-day/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="‘Darwin’ Day"/><published>2021-03-05T19:26:55+00:00</published><updated>2021-03-05T19:26:55+00:00</updated><id>https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2021/darwin-day</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2021/darwin-day/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">“Independence, Defence and Resistance”</title><link href="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2020/independence-defence-and-resistance/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“Independence, Defence and Resistance”"/><published>2020-08-09T13:09:32+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-09T13:09:32+00:00</updated><id>https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2020/independence-defence-and-resistance</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2020/independence-defence-and-resistance/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry></feed>