<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://mishrakishan.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://mishrakishan.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-02-17T21:47:58+00:00</updated><id>https://mishrakishan.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Quantum Mechanics 101: Demystifying Its Postulates</title><link href="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/QuantumMech/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Quantum Mechanics 101: Demystifying Its Postulates"/><published>2025-02-17T05:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-17T05:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/QuantumMech</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/QuantumMech/"><![CDATA[<blockquote> <p><em>“If quantum mechanics hasn’t profoundly shocked you, you haven’t understood it yet.”</em><br/> – Niels Bohr</p> </blockquote> <p>Quantum mechanics is often described as one of the most mind-bending fields of physics, not just because of its abstract nature but because of the very real, fundamental concepts it reveals about our universe. As someone who first encountered quantum mechanics in my sophomore physics course, I can attest to the confusion and awe that come with it. From the strange notion of particles existing as a probability until observed, to the perplexing wavefunctions that govern everything, the journey through quantum mechanics is both intellectually thrilling and deeply perplexing.</p> <p>Over the years, whether through my undergraduate or master’s courses, I continuously encountered concepts that seemed illogical or even counterintuitive. Among these were ideas like the unitarity of operators, time evolution, time-dependent versus time-independent states, and the Hermiticity of operators. These principles often felt like abstract concepts, difficult to apply outside the classroom, especially when delving into more advanced courses like Quantum Field Theory. Often, it took multiple reviews, months of rethinking, and even fresh perspectives to make the connections.</p> <p>While quantum mechanics is an immensely powerful framework for understanding the microscopic world, it can be frustratingly abstract, requiring a solid understanding of both its mathematical structure and the physical intuition behind it. In this article, I aim to offer an accessible explanation of these foundational ideas for undergraduates or graduate students, with a focus on understanding quantum mechanics from a more tangible, relatable viewpoint.</p> <h2 id="classical-vs-quantum-the-idea-of-the-qubit">Classical vs Quantum: The idea of the Qubit</h2> <p>In classical mechanics, the most basic unit of information is the <strong>bit</strong>, which represents a binary value—either 0 or 1. Imagine these bits as simple “on” or “off” states, much like flipping a light switch.</p> <p>Quantum mechanics, however, introduces a new and strange concept: the <strong>quantum bit} or **qubit</strong>. Unlike a classical bit, a qubit can exist in a state that is both 0 and 1 simultaneously, a phenomenon known as <strong>superposition</strong>.</p> <p>A qubit is described mathematically as:</p> \[|\psi\rangle = \alpha |0\rangle + \beta |1\rangle\] <p>where $ \alpha $ and $ \beta $ are complex numbers that satisfy the normalization condition:</p> \[|\alpha|^2 + |\beta|^2 = 1\] <table> <tbody> <tr> <td>Here, $</td> <td>0\rangle $ and $</td> <td>1\rangle $ represent the classical bit states, but now, the qubit can exist in a linear combination of these states. The coefficients $ \alpha $ and $ \beta $ determine the probability amplitudes for the system being observed in either of these two states.</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>But what exactly is a qubit physically? To dive deeper into this, we turn to the <strong>postulates of quantum mechanics</strong> , which govern the behavior of quantum systems.</p> <h2 id="postulates-of-quantum-mechanics">Postulates of Quantum Mechanics</h2> <p>The postulates of quantum mechanics provide the foundational principles that govern the behavior of quantum systems. These postulates are the rules that form the structure of quantum mechanics, and they help explain phenomena such as wave-particle duality, superposition, and entanglement. Here is a summary of the key postulates:</p> <h2 id="postulate-1-state-representation-and-quantum-space">Postulate 1. State Representation and Quantum Space</h2> <table> <tbody> <tr> <td>In quantum mechanics, the state of a quantum system is represented by a <strong>vector</strong> in a <strong>complex vector space</strong> (specifically, a <strong>Hilbert space</strong>). We represent the state of a system as a <strong>ket</strong> $</td> <td>\psi\rangle $, a unit vector in this space. In the language of <strong>bra-ket notation</strong> developed by Paul Dirac, the corresponding <strong>bra</strong> $ \langle \psi</td> <td>$ is the dual of the ket.</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>In matrix form, the state $ |\psi\rangle $ is represented as a column vector, while the corresponding dual $ \langle \psi| $ is the conjugate transpose of that vector. For example, if we have a quantum system in a d-dimensional space, the state vector can be written as:</p> <p>\(|\psi\rangle = \begin{pmatrix} \alpha_1 \\ \alpha_2 \\ \vdots \\ \alpha_d \end{pmatrix}\) The corresponding dual (bra) would be the complex conjugate transpose of the ket:</p> \[\langle \psi| = (\alpha_1^*, \alpha_2^*, \dots, \alpha_d^*)\] <table> <tbody> <tr> <td>The <strong>inner product</strong> between two vectors $</td> <td>\psi\rangle $ and $</td> <td>\phi\rangle $ is defined as:</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> \[\langle \psi | \phi \rangle = \sum_i \alpha_i^* \beta_i\] <p>This gives a scalar quantity, and the <strong>outer product</strong> (ket-bra) results in a matrix:</p> \[|\psi\rangle \langle \phi|\] <p>This is the basis for constructing linear operators on the state space. The outer product (ket-bra) produces a matrix, and these matrices can be interpreted as linear operators acting on vectors within a vector space.</p> <h3 id="the-normalization-condition">The Normalization Condition</h3> <p>Quantum states are <strong>normalized</strong>, meaning the total probability of finding the system in any of its possible states must be 1. This normalization condition is written as:</p> \[\langle \psi | \psi \rangle = 1\] <p>This condition is referred to as the <strong>normalization condition}. It is not a purely mathematical constraint, but rather arises from a physical consideration, namely, the **conservation of probabilities</strong>. The components of this vector are probability amplitudes, and thus the square of these amplitudes must sum to 1.</p> <blockquote> <table> <tbody> <tr> <td>If $</td> <td>\psi\rangle \in \mathcal{H} $, then any scalar multiple $ \lambda</td> <td>\psi\rangle $ is also an element of $ \mathcal{H} $, where $ \lambda $ is a scalar. Physically, $ \psi $ and $ \lambda</td> <td>\psi\rangle $ represent the same quantum state, as $ \lambda $ does not produce any observable distinction. Therefore, quantum states are defined up to an overall scale, which is often referred to as the “overall phase.” This freedom allows us to normalize the vector, which does not alter the state itself.</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> </blockquote> <h3 id="two-level-quantum-systems-the-qubit">Two-Level Quantum Systems: The Qubit}</h3> <p>The simplest example of a quantum system is a <strong>two-level system</strong>, which is the quantum analog of a classical bit. The state space of such a system is described by two orthogonal states, $ |0\rangle $ and $ |1\rangle $. These states are often called the **computational basis}.</p> <p><strong>Physical examples of two-level systems</strong> include:</p> <ul> <li> <p>The <strong>polarization of light</strong>, with horizontal $ |H\rangle $ and vertical $ |V\rangle $ polarization states. A general polarization state is: \(|P\rangle = \alpha |H\rangle + \beta |V\rangle \in \mathbb{C}^2\) We can also identify these states as:</p> <p>\(|H\rangle = |0\rangle, \quad |V\rangle = |1\rangle\) The polarization states of light can be described as quantum superpositions, where the light can exist in a state that is simultaneously horizontal and vertical polarization. This concept is fundamental to quantum optics and quantum information theory.</p> </li> <li> <table> <tbody> <tr> <td>The <strong>spin of particles</strong> The spin of a particle (such as an electron or proton) can be probed by an external magnetic field. In the presence of a magnetic field, the particle’s spin states are described as spin-up and spin-down states. These correspond to the two-level system with states $</td> <td>0\rangle $ and $</td> <td>1\rangle $:</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> \[|\Psi\rangle = \alpha |\uparrow\rangle + \beta |\downarrow\rangle \in \mathbb{C}^2\] <p>The spin of these particles is a crucial quantum property, and when measured along any axis (typically the $z-$axis), the spin is quantized into two distinct eigenstates—up and down—resulting in a binary state space. This concept forms the basis for many quantum technologies, including quantum computing and quantum cryptography.</p> </li> <li> <table> <tbody> <tr> <td><strong>Two-level atoms (Superconducting Qubits)</strong> In a system with a two-level atom, there are two distinct energy levels: the ground state $</td> <td>G\rangle $ and the excited state $</td> <td>E\rangle $. The state is described as:</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> \[|\Psi\rangle = \alpha |G\rangle + \beta |E\rangle \in \mathbb{C}^2\] <p>In atoms, quantum mechanics allows for the existence of discrete energy levels, and a two-level atom can exist in a superposition of these energy states. This phenomenon is crucial in many areas, such as quantum optics, laser physics, and the study of atomic transitions. The ability of an atom to exist in a superposition of ground and excited states is also the foundation of quantum information processing.</p> </li> </ul> <p>The state of a qubit can always be written as a linear combination of these two basis states:</p> \[|\psi\rangle = \alpha |0\rangle + \beta |1\rangle\] <p>This is the essence of <strong>quantum superposition</strong>—the ability for a qubit to exist in both states at once.</p> <h3 id="the-bloch-sphere">The Bloch Sphere</h3> <p>Because the state of a qubit is represented by two complex numbers (i.e., $ \alpha $ and $ \beta $), we can parameterize these states in terms of **two real angles}—$\theta$ and $\phi$:</p> \[\alpha = \cos\left(\frac{\theta}{2}\right) e^{i \phi_{\alpha}}, \quad \beta = \sin\left(\frac{\theta}{2}\right) e^{i \phi_{\beta}}\] <p>where $ \theta \in [0, \pi] $ and $ \phi_{\alpha}, \phi_{\beta} \in [0, 2\pi] $, due to the overall phase freedom of the state.</p> <p>Thus, the qubit state can be expressed as:</p> <p>\(|\Psi\rangle = \cos\left(\frac{\theta}{2}\right) e^{i \phi_{\alpha}} |0\rangle + \sin\left(\frac{\theta}{2}\right) e^{i \phi_{\beta}} |1\rangle\) or equivalently,</p> <p>\(|\Psi\rangle = e^{i \phi_{\alpha}} \left[\cos\left(\frac{\theta}{2}\right) |0\rangle + \sin\left(\frac{\theta}{2}\right) e^{i (\phi_{\beta} - \phi_{\alpha})} |1\rangle \right]\) This representation describes the state as a point on the surface of a sphere in 3D space, known as the <strong>Bloch sphere</strong>.</p> <h3 id="basis-states-and-transformations">Basis States and Transformations</h3> <table> <tbody> <tr> <td>A vector space can have <strong>infinitely many basis states</strong>. In addition to the standard computational basis $ {</td> <td>0\rangle,</td> <td>1\rangle} $, the qubit space can also have other valid basis sets. Two alternative orthonormal basis states for $ \mathbb{C}^2 $ are:</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> \[|+\rangle = \frac{1}{\sqrt{2}} (|0\rangle + |1\rangle), \quad |-\rangle = \frac{1}{\sqrt{2}} (|0\rangle - |1\rangle)\] <p>These states form a new orthonormal basis, and we can verify the orthogonality: \(\langle + | - \rangle = \langle - | + \rangle = 0, \quad \langle + | + \rangle = \langle - | - \rangle = 1\)</p> <table> <tbody> <tr> <td>Thus, $ {</td> <td>+\rangle,</td> <td>-\rangle} $ also forms an orthonormal basis for the qubit state space.</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>We can also define another set of basis states:</p> \[|i\rangle = \frac{1}{\sqrt{2}} (|0\rangle + i |1\rangle), \quad |-i\rangle = \frac{1}{\sqrt{2}} (|0\rangle - i |1\rangle)\] <table> <tbody> <tr> <td>The set $ {</td> <td>i\rangle,</td> <td>-i\rangle} $ forms another orthonormal basis for the qubit state space $ \mathbb{C}^2 $.</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>These new basis states are related to the computational basis via a <strong>unitary transformation</strong>, which is a linear transformation that preserves the inner product of vectors.</p> <table> <tbody> <tr> <td>These different basis sets are related through a linear transformation. For example, the transformation between the computational basis $ {</td> <td>0\rangle,</td> <td>1\rangle} $ and the $ {</td> <td>+\rangle,</td> <td>-\rangle} $ basis can be represented by a linear operator, such as the Hadamard operator $ H $:</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> \[H |0\rangle = |+\rangle = \frac{1}{\sqrt{2}} (|0\rangle + |1\rangle), \quad H |1\rangle = |-\rangle = \frac{1}{\sqrt{2}} (|0\rangle - |1\rangle)\] <p>This transformation can be written in terms of outer products:</p> \[\mathcal{H} = \frac{1}{\sqrt{2}} \left( |+\rangle \langle 0| + |-\rangle \langle 1| \right)\] <p>Alternatively, it can be expressed as:</p> \[\mathcal{H} = \frac{1}{\sqrt{2}} \left( |0\rangle \langle 0| + |1\rangle \langle 0| + |0\rangle \langle 1| - |1\rangle \langle 1| \right)\] <h3 id="matrix-representation">Matrix Representation</h3> <p>The state vectors $ |0\rangle $ and $ |1\rangle $ are represented as column vectors: \(|0\rangle = \begin{pmatrix} 1 \\ 0 \end{pmatrix}, \quad |1\rangle = \begin{pmatrix} 0 \\ 1 \end{pmatrix}\) The alternative basis states $ |+\rangle $ and $ |-\rangle $ are represented as: \(|+\rangle = \frac{1}{\sqrt{2}} \begin{pmatrix} 1 \\ 1 \end{pmatrix}, \quad |-\rangle = \frac{1}{\sqrt{2}} \begin{pmatrix} 1 \\ -1 \end{pmatrix}\)</p> <p>Using these, we can express the Hadamard operator $ H $ as:</p> <p>\(H = \frac{1}{\sqrt{2}} \begin{pmatrix} 1 &amp; 1 \\ 1 &amp; -1 \end{pmatrix}\) The Hadamard gate is an important quantum operation that transforms the computational basis states into the $ {|+\rangle, |-\rangle} $ basis.</p> <h2 id="postulate-2-observables-and-operators">Postulate 2. Observables and Operators</h2> <p>Quantum mechanics also provides a framework for understanding <strong>observables</strong>, which are quantities we can measure in a quantum system. In classical mechanics, observables are just real numbers (like position or momentum), but in quantum mechanics, observables are represented by <strong>Hermitian operators</strong>. As we mentioned, states in quantum systems are represented as vectors, and they transform according to linear transformations. There are two important classes of linear operators we are concerned with:</p> <h3 id="1-hermitian-matricesoperators">1. Hermitian Matrices/Operators</h3> <p>A matrix or operator $ H $ is called <strong>Hermitian</strong> if it satisfies the following condition:</p> \[H = (H^*)^T = H^{\dagger}\] <p>where $ H^{\dagger} $ is the <strong>adjoint</strong> of the linear operator, which refers to the complex conjugate transpose of $ H $. Hermitian operators are also often referred to as <em>self-adjoint</em> operators.</p> <h3 id="properties-of-hermitian-matrices">Properties of Hermitian Matrices:</h3> <ul> <li><strong>Real Eigenvalues:</strong> Hermitian matrices have real eigenvalues.</li> <li><strong>Diagonalizability:</strong> Hermitian matrices are diagonalizable, meaning they can be expressed in diagonal form in some orthonormal basis.</li> </ul> <h3 id="example-hermitian-operator-for-a-two-level-system">Example: Hermitian Operator for a Two-Level System</h3> <p>Consider the spin operator $ S_z $ for a spin-1/2 particle. Its matrix representation is:</p> <p>\(S_z = \frac{\hbar}{2} \begin{pmatrix} 1 &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; -1 \end{pmatrix}\) Other spin operators such as $ S_x $ and $ S_y $ are also Hermitian.</p> <h3 id="why-are-hermitian-operators-important-in-quantum-mechanics">Why are Hermitian operators important in quantum mechanics?</h3> <p>Postulate 2 in quantum mechanics states that <em>physical quantities</em> or observables are associated with Hermitian operators} on the system’s Hilbert space. The eigenvalues of these Hermitian operators correspond to the possible values that the physical quantity can take.</p> <p>For example, in the case of a spin-1/2 system:</p> <ul> <li> <table> <tbody> <tr> <td>The states $</td> <td>0\rangle =</td> <td>1/2\rangle = \begin{pmatrix} 1 \ 0 \end{pmatrix} $ and $</td> <td>1\rangle =</td> <td>-1/2\rangle = \begin{pmatrix} 0 \ 1 \end{pmatrix} $ are used to represent spin states.</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> </li> <li> <p>For $ S_z $, we have the eigenvalue equations:</p> \[S_z |0\rangle = \frac{\hbar}{2} |0\rangle\] \[S_z |1\rangle = -\frac{\hbar}{2} |1\rangle\] <p>These are eigenvalue equations, implying that $ S_z $ is the observable associated with the spin along the z-axis. In contrast, for $ S_x $, we get:</p> \[S_x |0\rangle = \frac{\hbar}{2} |1\rangle\] \[S_x |1\rangle = \frac{\hbar}{2} |0\rangle\] <table> <tbody> <tr> <td>These are not eigenvalue equations, so $ S_x $ cannot be directly associated with a single value in this basis. However, when we express $ S_x $ in the $ {</td> <td>+\rangle,</td> <td>-\rangle} $ basis (the eigenstates of $ S_x $), we find:</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> \[S_x |+\rangle = \frac{\hbar}{2} |+\rangle\] </li> </ul> \[S_x |-\rangle = \frac{\hbar}{2} |-\rangle\] <p>This makes $ S_x $ an observable associated with the spin component along the x-axis.</p> <table> <tbody> <tr> <td>The matrix representations of these operators in the $ {</td> <td>0\rangle,</td> <td>1\rangle} $ basis are:</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>\(S_z = \frac{\hbar}{2} \left( |0\rangle \langle 0| - |1\rangle \langle 1| \right)\) and</p> <p>\(S_x = \frac{\hbar}{2} \left( |0\rangle \langle 1| + |1\rangle \langle 0| \right)\) These can also be written in the $ {|+\rangle, |-\rangle} $ basis:</p> \[S_x = \frac{\hbar}{2} \left( |+\rangle \langle -| + |-\rangle \langle +| \right)\] <h3 id="2-unitary-operators">2. Unitary Operators</h3> <p>A matrix or operator $ U $ is <em>unitary</em> if it satisfies the following condition:</p> <p>\(U^{\dagger} U = U U^{\dagger} = I\) where $ I $ is the identity matrix. An example of a unitary operator is the <em>Hadamard operator</em> $ H $, which is given by:</p> <p>\(H = \frac{1}{\sqrt{2}} \begin{pmatrix} 1 &amp; 1 \\ 1 &amp; -1 \end{pmatrix}\) The Hadamard operator acts on the computational basis states as follows:</p> <p>\(H |0\rangle = |+\rangle, \quad H |1\rangle = |-\rangle\) The Hadamard operator is both <em>Hermitian</em> and <em>unitary</em>, meaning:</p> \[H^{\dagger} = H \quad \text{and} \quad H H^{\dagger} = I\] <h3 id="why-are-unitary-operators-important">Why are unitary operators important?</h3> <p>Unitary operators are crucial in quantum mechanics, particularly for describing <em>time evolution</em> of quantum systems.</p> <h2 id="postulate-3-time-evolution-how-do-quantum-systems-evolve-with-time">Postulate 3: Time Evolution (How do Quantum Systems Evolve with Time?)</h2> <p>One of the most fundamental questions in quantum mechanics is how quantum systems evolve over time. This evolution is governed by the <strong>Schrödinger equation</strong>, which describes how the state of a quantum system changes with time.</p> <table> <tbody> <tr> <td>The evolution of quantum systems over time is governed by <em>unitary transformations</em>. If $</td> <td>\psi(t_0)\rangle $ represents the state of the system at time $ t_0 $, the state at time $ t $ is given by:</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> <p>\(|\psi(t)\rangle = U(t, t_0) |\psi(t_0)\rangle\) where $ U(t, t_0) $ is the <em>unitary time evolution operator</em>. This operator governs how quantum states evolve over time.</p> <p>The time evolution is driven by a <em>Hermitian operator</em> called the <em>Hamiltonian</em> $ H $, which is associated with the energy of the system. The Schrödinger equation describes the time evolution of the system:</p> <p>\(i \hbar \frac{\partial}{\partial t} |\psi(t)\rangle = H |\psi(t)\rangle\) For time-independent Hamiltonians, the solution to the Schrödinger equation is:</p> <p>\(|\psi(t)\rangle = \textcolor{red}{e^{i H(t - t_0)/\hbar}} |\psi(t_0)\rangle\) The term $ \textcolor{red}{e^{i H(t - t_0)/\hbar}} $ is the unitary time evolution operator $ \textcolor{red}{U(t, t_0)} $.</p> <h3 id="why-must-time-evolution-be-unitary">Why must time evolution be unitary?</h3> <p>To preserve the <em>norm</em> of the quantum state (since probabilities must sum to 1), the time evolution operator must be unitary. That is, for the initial state $ |\psi(t_0)\rangle $ with norm 1: \(\langle \psi(t_0) | \psi(t_0) \rangle = 1\) The final state $ |\psi(t)\rangle $ will also have norm 1:</p> <p>\(\langle \psi(t) | \psi(t) \rangle = \langle \psi(t_0) | U^{\dagger} U | \psi(t_0) \rangle = \langle \psi(t_0) | \psi(t_0) \rangle = 1\) Thus, unitary transformations preserve the norm of the state vector, making them essential for quantum mechanics.</p> <p>Unitary time evolution operators form the <em>quantum gates</em> used in quantum computation, where single qubit gates are represented by 2x2 unitary matrices such as the Hadamard gate $ H $.</p> <h3 id="properties-of-the-time-evolution-operator--ut-t_0-">Properties of the Time Evolution Operator $ U(t, t_0) $:</h3> <ul> <li> <p><strong>Composition:</strong> The time evolution operator satisfies:</p> <p>\(U(t_2, t_0) = U(t_2, t_1) U(t_1, t_0) \quad \text{for} \quad t_0 \leq t_1 \leq t_2\) This property allows us to compose quantum gates in sequences.</p> </li> <li> <p><strong>Inverses:</strong> The inverse of the time evolution operator is:</p> <p>\(U^{\dagger}(t, t_0) = U(t_0, t)\) This implies that quantum gates are <strong>reversible</strong>, a fundamental characteristic of quantum mechanics.</p> </li> </ul> <h2 id="postulate-4-measurement-and-probability">Postulate 4: Measurement and Probability</h2> <p>So far, we have seen that a quantum system or state must be represented by a unitary matrix, and it evolves over time through unitary transformations. Physical quantities are associated with Hermitian operators. But how do we know what physical values correspond to these quantities, and what is the process of measurement?</p> <p>The process of <strong>measurement</strong> in quantum mechanics is not as straightforward as in classical mechanics. In classical mechanics, measurements can give us a definite value, but quantum mechanics introduces an element of uncertainty. When measuring physical quantities, the set of eigenvalues of the corresponding Hermitian operator gives the possible values that can be obtained from the measurement. Naturally, there is a probabilistic element to the quantum measurement process.</p> <ul> <li> <table> <tbody> <tr> <td>Let $ A $ be a Hermitian operator (observable) with eigenvalues $ {a_i} $ and eigenstates $</td> <td>a_i\rangle $, where $ i = 1, \dots, d $. Then, the postulate says that measuring the observable $ A $ on the state $</td> <td>\psi\rangle $ gives the outcome $ a_i $ with probability:</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> \[P_i = |\langle \psi | a_i \rangle|^2.\] </li> <li> <p>If you know the state of the system, you can predict the possible outcomes and their respective probabilities. However, each time you measure the system, you cannot predict which specific outcome will occur. By repeating the experiment many times, you can extract statistical data about the measurement outcomes.</p> </li> <li> <table> <tbody> <tr> <td><strong>Post-measurement state</strong>: After obtaining the outcome $ a_i $, the state $</td> <td>\psi\rangle $ collapses to the corresponding eigenstate $</td> <td>a_i\rangle $. More precisely, the state projects onto the eigenstate $</td> <td>a_i\rangle $ associated with the measured value.</td> </tr> </tbody> </table> </li> </ul> <script type="text/tikz">
\begin{tikzpicture}[scale=1.0]
    \tikzstyle myBG=[line width=3pt,opacity=1.0]

    \newcommand{\drawLatticeLine}[2]
    {
        \draw[gray!60, thick] (#1) -- (#2);
    }

    \newcommand{\drawDashedLine}[2]
    {
        \draw[red,line width = 2pt, opacity = 0.7] (#1) -- (#2);
    }

    \drawDashedLine{1,1}{1,4};
    \drawDashedLine{1,1}{4,1};
    \drawDashedLine{4,1}{4,4};
    \drawDashedLine{4,4}{1,4};

    \draw[violet,myBG] (-0.5,2.5) -- (1,2.5);
    \draw[violet,myBG] (4,1.5) -- (6,1.5);
    \draw[violet,myBG] (4,2) -- (6,2);
    \draw[violet,myBG, opacity = 1] (4,2.5) -- (6,2.5);
    \draw[violet,myBG, opacity = 1] (4,3) -- (6,3);
    \draw[violet,myBG, opacity = 1] (4,3.5) -- (6,3.5);

    \draw[violet, thick,fill=violet] (-0.5,2.5) circle (0.5cm);
    \node[anchor=center,scale=2.0] at (-0.5,2.5) {\scriptsize \textcolor{white}{$|\Psi\rangle$}};

    \node[anchor=center,scale=2.0] at (2.5,2.5) { \textcolor{red}{$A$}};
    \node[anchor=center,scale=1.0] at (2.5,2.0) { \textcolor{red}{(Apparatus)}};

    \draw[violet, thick,fill=violet] (5,3.5) circle (0.23cm);
    \node[anchor=center,scale=0.9] at (5,3.5) {\scriptsize \textcolor{white}{$|a_1\rangle$}};
    \draw[violet, thick,fill=violet] (5,3) circle (0.23cm);
    \node[anchor=center,scale=0.9] at (5,3) {\scriptsize \textcolor{white}{$|a_2\rangle$}};
    \draw[violet, thick,fill=violet] (5,2.5) circle (0.23cm);
    \node[anchor=center,scale=0.9] at (5,2.6) {\scriptsize \textcolor{white}{$\vdots$}};
    \draw[violet, thick,fill=violet] (5,2) circle (0.23cm);
    \node[anchor=center,scale=0.9] at (5,2.1) {\scriptsize \textcolor{white}{$\vdots$}};
    \draw[violet, thick,fill=violet] (5,1.5) circle (0.23cm);
    \node[anchor=center,scale=0.9] at (5,1.5) {\scriptsize \textcolor{white}{$|a_d\rangle$}};

    \draw[gray!60, thick,fill=blue] (6,3.3) rectangle +(0.6cm, 0.5cm);
    \node[anchor=center,scale=0.9] at (6.8,3.5) {\scriptsize \textcolor{white}{$P(1)$} with $a_1$};
    \draw[gray!60, thick,fill=blue] (6,2.8) rectangle +(0.6cm, 0.5cm);
    \node[anchor=center,scale=0.9] at (6.8,3) {\scriptsize \textcolor{white}{$P(2)$} with $a_2$};
    \draw[gray!60, thick,fill=blue] (6,2.3) rectangle +(0.6cm, 0.5cm);
    \node[anchor=center,scale=0.9] at (6.65,2.63) {\scriptsize \textcolor{white}{$\vdots$}~~~~ \Large\vdots};

    \draw[gray!60, thick,fill=blue] (6,1.8) rectangle +(0.6cm, 0.5cm);
    \node[anchor=center,scale=0.9] at (6.65,2.15) {\scriptsize \textcolor{white}{$\vdots$}~~~~ \Large\vdots};
    \draw[gray!60, thick, fill=blue] (6,1.3) rectangle +(0.6cm, 0.5cm);
    \node[anchor=center, scale=0.9] at (6.8,1.5) {\scriptsize \textcolor{white}{$P(d)$} with $a_d$};

\end{tikzpicture}
</script> <h2 id="basic-quantum-mechanics-on-qiskit">Basic Quantum Mechanics on Qiskit</h2> <div class="language-liquid highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>{::nomarkdown}
<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">assign</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">jupyter_path</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">=</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s1">'assets/jupyter/Basic_Quantum_Mechanics_with_Qiskit.ipynb'</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="p">|</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nf">relative_url</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>
<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">capture</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">notebook_exists</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">file_exists</span><span class="w"> </span>assets/jupyter/Basic_Quantum_Mechanics_with_Qiskit.ipynb<span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">endcapture</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>
<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">if</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">notebook_exists</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="o">==</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="s1">'true'</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>
  <span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">jupyter_notebook</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nv">jupyter_path</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>
<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">else</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>
  &lt;p&gt;Sorry, the notebook you are looking for does not exist.&lt;/p&gt;
<span class="cp">{%</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="nt">endif</span><span class="w"> </span><span class="cp">%}</span>
{:/nomarkdown}
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="education"/><category term="physics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An introductory look at the core principles of quantum mechanics.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Darwin Day</title><link href="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/distill/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Darwin Day"/><published>2025-01-10T02:29:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-10T02:29:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/distill</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/distill/"><![CDATA[<blockquote> <p>Sexual Selection ensures that dudes get fancy dresses.</p> </blockquote> <p><img src="https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:720/format:webp/1*odFY9m9MBawrlUePhayATg.png" alt=""/></p> <p>(In Fig: Male Grandalas are blue and Females are the brown or grey ones.)</p> <p>Darwin, in a letter, wrote to Asa Gray, “The sight of a feather in a peacock’s tail, whenever I gaze on it, makes me sick!” The seeming impossibility of explaining the gorgeous but impractical long tail of peacock had been bothering him for some time. He was so curious to know what causes the sexual differences which require some degree of self-consciousness in the males, as weapons by which they fight for the female, or ornaments that attract the opposite sex.</p> <p>His previous theory of ‘Natural Selection’ could only operate to spread a particular feature through a population, no matter how advantageous it might be if the individuals who possessed it, managed to breed and pass it on. Sexual differences between male and female of the same species had bothered him for a long time.</p> <p>But what are the apparent differences between the sexes? As it’s been observed, exotic colour in insects and birds, ornaments like ruffs and crests, the longer manes in male humans, Antlers or horns being so much smaller, or completely absent in some female deer or cattle, the contrasting bright and drab plumage of so many male and female birds and butterflies.</p> <p>After a long period of observation, he came with the idea of Sexual Selection. It’s a mechanism operating alongside natural selection which determines the sexual difference between male and female of the same species. It is a mechanism of two parts — involving physical adaptation in males, but also the aesthetic sense in females, which in many cases played a crucial role in selecting males.</p> <p>“The essence of Darwin’s disruptive genius was his ability to think about nature not as facts— but as a process, as progression, as history,” Mukherjee writes. Darwin’s genius was the awe-inspiring idea of Natural Selection. On December 27, 1831, he circumnavigated from Plymouth, England on HMS Beagle and headed towards Cape Verde to reach the shore of his intimate inquisitiveness surveying expedition of the southern Atlantic and Pacific oceans. As a scientist-in-training his never-ending thoughts of collecting, observing and noticing anything worthy to be noted made him sail the boat for five long years across many islands. During his journey as he writes in his book The Origin of Species, that he strongly felt lonely, nauseated, and dehydrated at times while surviving on a diet of dry raisins and bread. He kept believing in and reminding himself to stay calm and mentally healthy to avoid any propensity for impatience, inaccuracy and misery. As the journey went on, the expected evolutionary biological traits perplexed and thrilled him with joy and confidence, that he began writing and scribbling in his notes and journals. He observed and drew finches, penguins, birds, animals encountered throughout his journey. After five years when he returned to England, his drawings were the evidence of his proposed groundbreaking scientific work and the profound idea of natural selection that he almost had formulated and thoerised. But he was wary to reveal his collection and theories as they were completely contradicting the existed biblical narratives on the origin of species. He writes, “In natural selection, organisms with genetic variations that suit their environment tend to propagate more descendants than organisms of the same species that lack the variation, thus influencing the overall genetic makeup of the species”. Later on, this idea solved many underlying and lurking religious orthodox, biblical stories, biological mysteries and puzzles.</p> <p><img src="https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:720/format:webp/1*rtIJQkPfa1neEWflYvD2tw.jpeg" alt=""/></p> <blockquote> <p><em>The gene — An intimate History’ by Siddharth Mukherjee</em> In his drawing, there was no centre (as in Christianity, God firmly is placed at epicentre: all animals, created by him sprayed outward from the moment of creation). The thirteen types of finches he drew were not created by some divine whim, but by “natural descent” — cascading downward and upward from an original ancestral finch, he asserted.</p> </blockquote> <p><img src="https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:720/format:webp/0*PjEmLTdraH14lLT5.jpg" alt=""/></p> <blockquote> <p><em>A portrait of Charles Darwin and Title Page of ‘The Origin Of Species</em></p> </blockquote> <p>Later, on November 24, 1859, his first book “The Origin of Species” endorsing the theory of Natural Selection and the fundamentals of biological evolution was published. His theory that time was not formally accepted as it was very challenging to the previously acquired wisdom of humankind. It took a while for our society to accept the scientific challenges Darwin made based on the shreds of evidence he collected, a life span he spent and devoted to observations, understandings and pursuit of science. His theory received a general acceptance around 1882, after 52 years of social struggle, almost when Darwin had the last moments of his gratifying endeavour and the invaluable contribution he made to the scientific societies.</p> <p>After he received a good amount of acceptance (validation) to his theory, postcolonial societies led by industrial revolutions extracted a set of ideologies as ‘Social Darwinism’ to define social, political and economic views when imperialism, racism and inequalities were breeding at an immense rate in the society. Darwins’ theory of evolution and Social Darwinism are two different theories where the former is a biological evolution that progresses by sharing biological traits genetically and the later is a societal change that shares morality, intelligence, strength, frugality and many more. Darwin completely despised the transferring-evolution of social values developed by humankind through generations.</p> <p><img src="https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fit:640/format:webp/0*JcuJI7j-Ob8skckf.jpg" alt=""/></p> <blockquote> <p><em>Photo: Westminster Abbey Library</em> As an afterthought, he added “I think” above the page, as if to signal is the last point of departure from the mainland of biological and theological thoughts. His proposition “I think” above societal incongruity that all species have descended from a common ancestor is now a fundamental concept in science and the idea of survival “Natural Selection: endless forms and most beautiful and most wonderful have been, are being, evolved” is the grassroots of evolutionary biology.</p> </blockquote> <p>==Sometimes we need to really challenge our collective accepted wisdom in order to move forward. Because as long and as much time any theory or wisdom takes to transcend the physical time and persists in society, it gets harder and harder to challenge them and invalidate its gravity.==</p> <p><strong>Science and Technology continuously have been advancing with the progressiveness of society and research but in molecular and evolutionary biology Darwin’s genius and ideas have always remained central to the field.</strong></p> <p>Note: The following (<em>“A beautiful flock of grandalas!”</em>) contrasting colours and subtle differences were also studied by the Handicap Principle supported by many Evolutionary biologists, and is why peacocks have such long tails, even though they are a burden for flight and evading predators.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="writing"/><category term="darwin"/><category term="sexualselection"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Sexual Selection]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Still Vulnerable at 25</title><link href="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/twitter/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Still Vulnerable at 25"/><published>2025-01-10T02:29:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-10T02:29:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/twitter</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/twitter/"><![CDATA[<p>The chair of solitude is so comforting until it’s an unexplainable, suffocating silence that rebels against the pursuit of “living a life in love’, recognition, pity, validation or attention other than any honest attempt to communicate an understanding.” If building castles in the air would be one thing, building haunted devil mansions would be another. And realisation hits hard, and you fall down into an inward spiral in the depths of nowhere.</p> <p>The hot coffee would steam on a bright sunny day as you sit bored on your couch. Unwilling to move muscles, you would remain there, staring into the void while your brain would start to do “the talking”. The talks, most of, if not all the time, would be dark. Scared, you start craving activity. Yet, you wouldn’t want to cut ties with lethargy without a proper closure. So, you would start with a gentle peek out of the window. Muscle movement achieved! Like a yorker right into the black hole, the sun would slap your face tight. “The window was there for a reason!”, your brain wouldn’t seem to give up. You would stare at the world outside. You would wonder at a white feather being kissed by the winds, shining as its manoeuver past you! You would start falling in love with almost everything that you see through the window. “I see. Now what about this?”, our brain cuts in. Then, you would table-fan your head slightly to the sides to find gigantic wings on either side of your shoulders. “Hehe!”, the asshole of a brain would give you a manipulative laugh. It would make you want to use the wings because flying high would give you a different form of high. Adding fuel to the fire, the typical midsummer breeze outside the window would stage a ballet in your face. ” This gets interesting”, your brain grabs a popcorn while you stay there like a total jackass gridlocked by the two differently haunting weapons of choice. The window would almost slap harder as the breeze starts gusting, if not for the latch. It doesn’t stop there. The rooftop that’d been watching everything just above you blows out open and you see light entering and skies smiling at you.</p> <p>One of the quotes by Camus hits right in my face of vulnerability every time I get stuck in a situation like this,</p> <p><em>Sad to still feel so vulnerable. In 25 years I’ll be 57. 25 years then to create a body of work and to find what I’m looking for. After that, old age and death. I know what is most important for me. And I still find a way to give in to little temptations, wasting time of frivolous conversations or fruitless idling about. I’ve mastered two or three things in myself. But how far I am from the kind of superiority that I so badly need.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="writing"/><category term="solitude"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The chair of solitude is so comforting until it’s an unexplainable, suffocating silence that rebels against the pursuit of “living a life in love’, recognition, pity, validation or attention other than any honest attempt to communicate an understanding.” If building castles in the air would be one thing, building haunted devil mansions would be another. And realisation hits hard, and you fall down into an inward spiral in the depths of nowhere.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Still Vulnerable at 25.</title><link href="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/still-vulnerable-at-25/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Still Vulnerable at 25."/><published>2025-01-09T20:59:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-09T20:59:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/still-vulnerable-at-25</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/still-vulnerable-at-25/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Chair of Solitude]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">writing thrusts me into uncharted territory | froggy 🍃</title><link href="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/writing-thrusts-me-into-uncharted-territory-froggy/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="writing thrusts me into uncharted territory | froggy 🍃"/><published>2025-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/writing-thrusts-me-into-uncharted-territory--froggy-</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/writing-thrusts-me-into-uncharted-territory-froggy/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[there's lots of discourse on writing in the Bear Den (lol). the purposes of writing, who you should write for, why you should write, etc. All great discussio...]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">the ‘return to office’ lies | ava’s blog</title><link href="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/the-return-to-office-lies-avas-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="the ‘return to office’ lies | ava’s blog"/><published>2025-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/the-return-to-office-lies--avas-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/the-return-to-office-lies-avas-blog/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[i vent about return to office bullshittery.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Love is a funny thing.</title><link href="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/disqus-comments/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Love is a funny thing."/><published>2025-01-07T03:44:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-07T03:44:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/disqus-comments</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/disqus-comments/"><![CDATA[<p>Love is a funny thing. You expect it to be easy. You expect it to be a world of roses and laughs and perfect moments that you find only in movies. You expect your partner to always say the right thing and always know exactly how you feel, or exactly how to react to it. You expect them to calm you down when you’re yelling or to chase you when you run away. You expect so much that you feel entirely, and utterly defeated when something doesn’t exactly match up with all your plans. But that’s the thing, love isn’t a plan. Love is a feeling. It’s that feeling you get when you know you are going to see that person. You are always counting down the minutes, the hours, the days or even months until you will see them again because you love that feeling you have when you are with them.</p> <p>Love is a feeling of perfect happiness. Being in their arms means that everything will be okay and even if it’s really not going to be, you’ll get a feeling that they’ll do whatever they can to make it be, or just to try to make you feel better. It’s that feeling that you are loved for who you are and you love them for who they are. It’s about how they are the first ones you want to talk to when anything is good or bad and how you are always learning something new no matter how long you’ve been together. It’s about changing and being a new person, not necessarily changing your ways or who you are, but wanting to be different and a better person simply cause that person is in your life and you want to be everything to them.</p> <p>Love doesn’t have a certain beginning and it certainly has no end or visible finish line to those deeply in it. Love happens, and it is so incredibly messy. You don’t just automatically love someone. you have to slowly learn to trust; Trust that they don’t cheat on you, trust that they don’t lie to you, trust that they truly admire you, trust that they will always be there for you, trust that they can go to a party and not get high or drunk, trust that you don’t have to worry about them breaking up with you the second you wake up, trust that they will stick up for you trust that you don’t have to worry about them breaking up with you the second you wake up, trust that they will stick up for you, trust that they will never fall in love with another, trust that they won’t just get sick of you, and trust that they want you, like you want them. You want to be with them more to the point where you’re jealous of anyone who tries to be with that person. Then it gets you mad but you get past it, you can’t be jealous anymore. You can’t because you have this undying confidence that this person will never leave you, they will never betray you, and that they would never pick someone else over you, that you’re irreplaceable. That’s when the confidence hits you, that you really do love each other and it’s unbreakable.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="writing"/><category term="love"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Love is a funny thing. You expect it to be easy. You expect it to be a world of roses and laughs and perfect moments that you find only in movies. You expect your partner to always say the right thing and always know exactly how you feel, or exactly how to react to it. You expect them to calm you down when you’re yelling or to chase you when you run away. You expect so much that you feel entirely, and utterly defeated when something doesn’t exactly match up with all your plans. But that’s the thing, love isn’t a plan. Love is a feeling. It’s that feeling you get when you know you are going to see that person. You are always counting down the minutes, the hours, the days or even months until you will see them again because you love that feeling you have when you are with them.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">why i write | ʕ•ᴥ•ʔ zypper</title><link href="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/why-i-write-zypper/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="why i write | ʕ•ᴥ•ʔ zypper"/><published>2025-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/why-i-write---zypper</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/why-i-write-zypper/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Inspired by Robert Birming’s “Why write“, I thought I would write my own spin-off and say why I do it.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Love is a funny thing.</title><link href="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/love-is-a-funny-thing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Love is a funny thing."/><published>2025-01-06T22:14:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-06T22:14:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/love-is-a-funny-thing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/love-is-a-funny-thing/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">how i deal with information overload | ʕ•ᴥ•ʔ zypper</title><link href="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/how-i-deal-with-information-overload-zypper/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="how i deal with information overload | ʕ•ᴥ•ʔ zypper"/><published>2025-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/how-i-deal-with-information-overload---zypper</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mishrakishan.github.io/blog/2025/how-i-deal-with-information-overload-zypper/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have developed a system for myself to remedy the large influx of information. Tying it all together is my note taking app that hosts my original thoughts.]]></summary></entry></feed>